Dr. Daniel Mortensen, PhD

DATA SCIENTIST

EXPERIENCE

DATA SCIENTIST I | DriveTime

JAN 2022 - CURRENT, TEMPE, AZ

- Develop machine learning models (logit, XGBoost) for prediction probability of loan default.
- Manage automated reporting for features impacting inventory pricing.
- Mentor upcoming talent.

Core Facility Director | Mass Spectrometry / Cell Sorting Assistant Professor of Chemistry | Brigham Young University

APR 2017 - AUG 2021, PROVO, UT

- Directed/performed A/B testing, hypothesis testing, experimental design, etc.
- Directed 2 core research facilities, about \$3 million in scientific equipment, 6 employees.
- Managed budgets, including charges, expenses, depreciations, and equipment purchases and repairs.
- Taught general chemistry and statistics in chemistry (~700 students).

EDUCATION

DataCamp | AS Equivalent: Data Science

OCT, 2021 - CURRENT, ONLINE

BrainStation | Diploma: Data Science

JULY - OCT 2021, ONLINE

UC Berkeley | PhD, Chemistry

JULY 2011 - 2016, BERKELEY, CA

8 peer reviewed publications, including one using MATLAB for modeling the motion of ions through a gas in a moving electric field. Received Richard A. Schaeffer Memorial Fund Travel Award.

PROJECTS

Regression Models for Predicting Commodity Sales Prices (link)

Various climate and market variables were used to model the annual and monthly sales price of US grain corn. 9 different regression models, including Logit, Kneighbors, and XGBoost, were tested. The best models were obtained using XGBRegressor, resulting in R^2 scores of 0.950 and 0.986 for annual and monthly prices, respectively.

dnmort@gmail.com 623-455-2133 www.linkedin.com/in/dnmort github.com/dnmort

PROFILE

I am a former chemistry professor turned data scientist. I feel like I've finally found my passion in data science. I love taking raw data and turning it into machine learning models that help drive company profitability. I love being able to make a measurable impact on the bottom line and figuring out ways to optimize that impact.

SKILLS

Statistics, SQL, Python, pandas, numpy, statsmodels, Hypothesis Testing, A/B testing, Parametric and non-Parametric Tests, Matplotlib, Plotly, Seaborn, Sklearn, Scikit-Learn, XGBoost, MATLAB, AWS, Jupyter, Tableau, Visual Basic, Command Line, Microsoft Office, Data Visualization, Presenting